Okay. You going well?
Yeah.
Morning, and welcome to the Mana
Wāhine Ministry for Women long-term insights briefing.
So thank you for coming, talking to the Social Services and Community Select
Committee this morning. And it's fine, it's all to you, leader.
Great. Thank you, Chair. Good morning, everyone.
It's great to be here this morning.
Are you comfortable if I say a few opening remarks and then-
Please do
...hand over for discussion? Fantastic.
So yeah, lovely to be here with you to talk about our long-term insights
briefing, Free to Lead: Tackling the Effects of Online Harm on the
Pipeline of Future Women Leaders.
I'm Kelly Coombs, Chief Executive of the Ministry for Women, and I'm joined by
members of my team, Anna Chalmers, who's the Deputy Secretary,
Engagement, Policy and Delivery, Mel Pearson, who is our Engagement
and Communications Manager, and also Kylie Fletcher, who
leads our Mana Wāhine Kaupapa inquiry, is joining us online as well.
So this briefing looks ahead at an issue that's already shaping the
conditions for women's participation and leadership and their safety in
our digital age.
We chose to focus on women in leadership because women's representation
in this sphere is crucial to achieving gender equality.
A key feature of that briefing is the voice and perspectives of
women, including young women.
Their experience show how online harm is already shaping
participation, influencing aspirations, and also the
choices that young women are making about leadership,
which can bring you into the spotlight in public life.
We are already seeing the impact of online abuse,
threats, harassment, and the impact this has on discouraging women
and girls from being visible, speaking up, sharing their
points of view and perspectives on issues, or pursuing leadership
roles.
Women often experience online harm differently to men,
with the abuse more likely to be gendered, sexualized,
appearance-focused, or directed at their credibility and their
right to speak.
These attacks can feel deeply personal and are often intended not
to just criticize a view, but to
intimidate, shame, or silence women from participating publicly.
We wanted this long-term insights briefing to be future-focused, but
also grounded in the Ministry's strategic priorities.
This briefing connects to our representation and
leadership strategic focus area, as well as our
safety one.
Looking over the longer term, this is about setting women up for success by
ensuring the environments they participate in, including
online spaces, are safe, enabling, and do not
place disproportionate barriers in the way of women's leadership.
The briefing doesn't make recommendations.
Instead, it pulls together evidence, stakeholder insights,
the perspectives and experience of women to put a broader
conversation about what needs to change so that women and girls can
participate confidently in public life, both now and in the
future. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I'll take the first one.
You can.
Thank you. Really interesting report,
and very concerning, to be honest.
But I see that there's a section in here around the social trends
globally towards women and how that's obviously
driving the algorithms. Can you just elaborate a little bit
further on your findings there and kind of what you're seeing from that
perspective?
Certainly.
So in terms of
global trends,
a
couple of years ago,
online harm and technology was a focus at the UN Commission on
the Status of Women. So this is definitely not an
issue that we're experiencing on our own.
It's something that's very front of mind
in these international gatherings when we're focused on gender equality.
And
it's a conversation also about
different ways in which this could be reshaped.
So some of the themes that come up there are the importance of growing the pipeline
of women and girls into STEM
training, but particularly engineering and
mathematics, so that they are involved in developing
future technologies, and also the importance of having women at the
governance tables of these companies that are leading the way
in terms of technology and innovation.
So that's part of the conversation there.
But absolutely, the impact that the online world is having on
women's ability to participate and owning that
leadership role is something that we are experiencing
globally.
In New Zealand,
every
two years, a survey's undertaken by the National Council of Women,
and I think some of the key findings of that survey speaks
to the points that you're making in your question also.
So, on the whole, that survey finds
that 79% of New Zealanders agree that gender
equality is a fundamental right. But
within that, 60% of those surveyed still
believe that sexism is an issue. And
when you're looking at the younger demographic, young men, so
in the 18 to 24-year-old cohort, are
over twice as likely as young women to believe that gender equality has gone too
far. And again, that is a
trend that we're seeing happening in other like-minded
countries in terms of some shifting views.
Mm.
Tenders.
Can I just hop on that? So, just in terms of those algorithms and what we're seeing
globally and the target on women, do you feel that there
needs to be some kind of responsibility because the big tech companies are
obviously driving some of those algorithms-
Yeah
... towards women? I mean, are men experiencing the same
targeting that we're seeing, not just in New Zealand, but in
other countries around the world?
Mm. So I think definitely the type of
experience of women and girls online is different.
Mm.
And I was at an event, I think it was last year, that
the speaker hosted where we had a panel of MPs, and on that
panel, men and women, and that was acknowledged by the men on the panel that
for them, their experience is that their ideas will be tested or
challenged-
Mm
... but less personal, whereas all of the women MPs on the panel,
their experience was quite different, that it was targeted to them as a woman, and
it wasn't actually about their ideas or point of view.
In terms of what we heard through this
research was that the women and the
girls who we engaged with
on the process, they talked about
wanting to see greater responsibility and accountability from platforms.
Mm.
So that was their perspective. They also spoke from their
point of view about having stronger laws and protections in place.
Mm.
But also keeping up with technology, which I think, as we
all appreciate, is quite challenging because it's so rapid
in its advancement.
A concept around
having safer spaces by design, and we can
talk to you a bit more about that if that's of interest.
Better education in digital literacy and clearer reporting
pathways to support people where they're affected by
online harm. They were some of the key themes that came
through. As well as the importance
for young women, in particular, to see role models.
So to see women in the public space
expressing their point of views, holding leadership roles that they could look up
to.
Mel, you might want to talk a little bit more about that.
Yeah. So from the young women and girls who
engaged with us as part of this process, they were largely in that 16 to
25 age group.
Yeah.
And for them, when they spoke about algorithms and mis and
disinformation online,
they really shared that they would appreciate more education.
So, how do you fact check something online?
What do you do when things go wrong?
And so for them, they placed a large emphasis on that early
education on digital literacy in schools in particular.
Mm.
They also spoke a lot about having safe spaces for them to
share and connect online.
Mm.
The online world is a big area for them to
socialize, for education, for example.
And so they just spoke about having places where they can connect that are
safe, and they know what to do to escalate things when they go wrong.
A key driver for us too, in our safety work more generally in
terms of the work we've done with Netsafe, we called it Free to
Lead. So resources for women to keep them
owning their space, and doing it in a safe way to support
employers to be looking after their
employees. But it is really, we
don't want women to step back from the online world because it's
so critical to
our lives, and it creates a lot of social and economic
opportunities for women. So that's sort of something we think about also in our
work more generally in this space.
And that is also another theme that comes up internationally.
It's
that some of the experiences that women are having, it can
silence them. It can make them choose to retreat
or to maybe not go for that leadership role that they had
aspirations for. So that is something we're very
mindful of, is
how to make the space work, the online space work, because it's
fundamental.
Well, just something interesting off something you said in your first answer
around encouraging young women and girls
into STEM subjects, and so they can actually help design these technologies that
shape
the future, basically. I'll share a brief,
quick anecdote. I visited United Machines in Dunedin with
Finance Minister Nicola Willis about a week and a half ago or something.
And the CEO
and co-owner, a lady called Sarah Ramsay, who's also the chair of United,
what have they got? Advanced Manufacturing Aotearoa.
And a lot of people probably don't know these kind of stories.
Mm.
How do we help get these stories out so young women, younger girls can
say, "These are people who are actually leading
advanced technology right now." And New Zealand's have really, really exciting
stuff that they're doing. Of course, you have advanced aerospace, medical
technology, et cetera. And it's quite awesome.
But how do we get those stories out there
more effectively? Any sort of thoughts on that?
Yeah.
That's a really good point. I think one of the really interesting areas that came
up through the report was opportunities to influence and needing to get more women
and girls into this space.
Mm.
So key to this, one of the potential areas is
safety by design, which is where systems are much more designed
with women in mind, women users. But in terms of that STEM piece, that's really
important for the development end.
So we're particularly seeing that with the rapid advancement of AI,
artificial intelligence, at the moment.
So if you look at STEM numbers-
There are on one level, more women are in STEM, but
that's because a large variety of them are in healthcare.
When you actually start to drill down and you look at ICT, we're looking at around
30%,
but certainly not at the senior management levels as well.
And that's where that STEM representation, that representation of women, is
quite vital to drive that. So absolutely, one of the roles of the ministry is to
share those stories and make sure that we're promoting that work.
That's definitely what we do through our channels and through our promotion of
work, and how we've started to develop some of those more deliverable
pieces to look into that space. But yes, no, I hear you.
You can't be what you can't see.
Mm.
And sharing those examples is a really good way of showing women that they can get
into that space, and that we have a role in helping drive that.
Mm.
That through.
I think in a way, also,
our strategic outcome areas are quite interconnected.
So safety is sort of that foundation that all women
need to succeed. And when we've been doing our gender
pay gap engagements across the country, we've met with some
really interesting businesses, just like the one you mentioned.
I remember a very
long-standing engineering business in Dunedin.
And so kind of on the surface you might think,
how many women would be there? What would the career pathways be?
But they're doing excellent work.
So we'll continue to look at excellent work in terms of creating pathways,
getting women into engineering and into leadership.
So we will continue to look for opportunities where we can, yeah, really
share those stories and
really amplify those experiences and put everything out on the
table. Another thing I thought was quite
reassuring was in the gender attitude survey that I
mentioned earlier. One of the
perspectives or one of the things that they look at there,
is sort of that differentiation between occupation of
men and occupation of women. And the large majority of New Zealanders
believe that roles, fields of study, et cetera,
should be open to men and women. So we've got that as the strong foundation here,
but telling those stories, I think continues to be really important.
Okay. That's helpful.
Okay. So
just what you raised there, that can go overnight.
I had a woman who, she's come from Afghanistan.
She was a family violence judge there.
We airlifted her out. For her,
that became a pathway that just was impossible overnight
in a society. And there are a whole lot of people trapped in that society
who just cannot
meet their potential whatsoever,
because the society's changed. Now with our
online
developments, there's trends out there that are just
completely misogynistic-
Mm
... that say women are to be trad wives,
and there are people buying into that kind of narrative.
Did you look at that, the fragility of the image
of leadership
for when they're, and what sort of pushback
we could organize? I'm particularly interested in the education issue,
and with men, with boys, young men.
Mm.
Yeah.
Just picking up on that last point, I think allies and
allyship is something that's
really important, and it's something that we are
bringing into our work. So, the resources that we
developed on the gender pay gap, many of those
stories have
male business owners talking about what they're doing to
understand, take action, address the gender pay gap in their
organization. So,
we've talked about really wanting to make sure that the
contribution of men and the role that men can play in
gender equality is something that's a feature of our work and how we think about
it.
The reason why we focused on this for our long-term
insights briefing, in part it's because we've got
this fantastic pipeline that's been developed over time
of women who are wanting to step into governance
roles. So we've got around 1,100 women on our Board Connector
database.
So that's fantastic. We've got that sitting there.
The environment they move into needs to be one that works for
them to,
like you said, meet their potential, deliver on their aspirations.
So we felt it was very important that we don't just think about
building the pipeline, but we're also thinking about that broader environment,
and that's the contribution that we wanted this briefing to
make.
Like I said, it's sort of not offering solutions, but we
can share the ideas and what the
aspirations are of the women that we engaged with as part of this
process.
I might just, we're just going short on time.
Sorry.
I'll just
Question.
Yeah, my question is really about, there's obviously no recommendations or
potential solutions in the briefing.
So we are too mixed in what cross-agency work are you doing,
to look for those solutions, because I think everybody actually knows the problem.
Yeah. Mm-hmm.
Like it's really obvious right now.
Yeah.
So it's more just, I think the biggest thing that
everyone grapples with is how to deal with the issues-
Mm
... and what the solution is. So have you guys, do you have a
second part of this work plan or are you working with others?
Ministries-
Yeah
... around that?
So it's a bit of both. So work we're leading on our own and work we're
connecting in with others.
So to give you a sense of some of the other work
that's being explored that we may be able to contribute to,
we've got close connections into the classifications office.
So currently they're thinking about
whether they repeat some research that they did looking into
misogyny, and we'd be able to work alongside them to support
that. They've also got some work under develop,
which is looking at,
picking up on your point, a lot of this is knowing, but, looking at whether
there's different trends and things coming through that we need to keep up with in
terms of the rapid
pace of change.
We've already got an established relationship with Netsafe.
One of the bits of work that we're picking up post our Free to Lead
work is working more with people who moderate
our social media pages so that
we're supporting them in their roles as moderators, which can also
make the space better for women and girls.
Mm-hmm.
And also connecting in with Ministry of Education in terms of the work that
they're leading on digital literacy.
So there's a lot of points of contact for us to make there.
In terms of what we're doing,
it was two weeks ago, we did some follow-up work to the stalking
legislation, so I brought a copy along just because it's so new.
We worked with Human Resources New Zealand and Shine to develop a
practical resource for employers
off the back of the stalking legislation, so that they can kind of
support their people who may be experiencing that.
So we'll continue to bring that focus on women's
economic empowerment and safety and see where the gaps are that we think we
can
add. So it's sort of contributing from the system perspective,
and then being quite practical about what are the things that we can do to make
a difference, to make sure these spaces are working for women and girls.
Supplementary, Cassandra.
Yeah, I had a supplementary on that because I think it's a really good point.
Obviously we need to look at solutions and where to go, because I suppose if
I look at, as a female public figure,
and the comments, they are
so unacceptable, some of the comments that you get.
And I think as public figures, we kind of go, "Oh, well,
we're in the public, so we just accept that." But what do you think we
should be doing when we get these really misogynist,
terrible, abusive-
Threatening
... comments that are on our feeds?
I'm sure other female members here are experiencing
the same, but I feel that it's getting worse, it's on the rise,
and-
Absolutely
... we just become more accepting because social media is obviously a platform to
be able to kind of get your message out there and get your narrative out there.
But I think the response from some people around the
country is just horrifying.
Yeah. Maybe I can make some
comments on that and then hand over to Anna to take a touch on some new tools that
have been developed that support that.
So, firstly, what we hear from women
is it's so important for you as leaders to be
holding your roles and in those roles, because they can see you there, it
grows their aspiration, and they want to follow in your
footsteps. Last week I met with
the visiting delegation of MPs from across the Pacific, in
the parliamentary exchange that was happening, and I was on a panel
alongside a member of Parliamentary Services who's focused on
all of your security.
So,
he was able to share some of the specific things that happen in our context,
and I guess with thinking forward about how they might be relevant in other
settings. But the message is really clear,
that
if woman MPs, if woman political leaders,
journalists, business leaders aren't visible,
that creates big issues. But absolutely how your
safety and wellbeing is
managed as part of that is really critical.
Because that's also what young women are looking at.
They're looking at you all and seeing the impact that it
might be having on you personally, the impact that it might be having on your
families and your children, and that can have a
really chilling impact on their ambition,
where they think that they can contribute.
I'll hand over to Anna just to talk about some other things we've learnt
about some tools that maybe can support you and others
when you're facing these unacceptable comments and
abuse.
Yeah, just would agree with that. And obviously, there is no single solution, which
is actually part of the biggest challenge here.
This has been an interesting meeting over in Paris with the OECD, looking at this
digital transformation and actually some of the really challenging
impacts for women in particular in office, and it's come up with
very similar findings around, New Zealand is absolutely not alone, and that
this rise is rapid. And so that any solutions need to be
multifaceted and involve a range of people, including the service providers
obviously themselves. And that really, taking that safety by
design,
and really working with them. But that needs a concerted effort.
We look a lot to Australia and the e-commissioner over there for some of the work
that they are doing, which is leading in this space.
I suppose more locally, there are some initiatives that have been developed.
One's called Face Forward. It's a recent development
which we are supporting as a ministry, and helping to support to be introduced
across
leading public figures in New Zealand.
It's free for use, and it is basically a technology that
blocks
these sorts of comments, and people are starting to use
it to quite a lot of success. So that's something that we would really encourage
and support, and really happy to share access into
the people at Oreto Labs that are doing that work at the moment.
But look, yes, watch this space, because it is something that we really
need to be focused on, and I think this is the opportunity with this outcome, is to
also help to share and bring some people together that can look at it in a more
concerted way as well. Unfortunately,
results from the last year's local body elections did show a decline in
women
representatives at the table, and that, for the ministry, is really key
because,
as you say, these gains for women's representation have been hard-fought.
So it's how do we come together and really work to try and
not make it such a challenging and terrible environment for
people in that public office, as well as the safety aspects to it.
Commissioner Warren.
I do. Thank you.
It is a bit of a sop to that, but I had two questions.
My other one was about the survey that you did.
Did you notice, or did you track the difference between urban and
rural in terms of the impact some of this is
having? So I'll leave that one with you.
But I just want to pick up on the conversation that we've been having.
And it always seems to me, maybe because I've got a few summers
behind me, that-
Don't worry
... I always hear that it's somebody else's problem to solve.
Yeah.
And from my point of view, picking up on what Catherine said about the comments-
Mm
... I don't get that on my social media feed.
Yeah.
And the reason is because if someone says anything negative-
Yes, Mel
... I block them.
Mm-hmm.
Problem solved. And so, we tend to think about the
issues as being someone else's issue.
But actually, what's going on that people can't do a simple thing
like turn their phone off or block people that say things you don't
like? It's very simple.
Yeah.
What's going on here?
It makes me think of when we did our
Behind the Keyboard series, which was when we had women
telling their stories, women with a public profile and really wanting to get these
issues out there. I remember one of the women talked about posting and
ghosting. So, to
say your piece, but then not to just-
Mm.
The way she kept herself safe was just to not look at the comments.
Or she did her thing, and she moved on to the next thing.
Yes.
So I just think it might've been something, too, that
could be a little bit generational.
Mel, I'm not sure if from our engagement with young women, whether they had a
different point of view on that.
Yeah. I think what
came through engagement is, particularly for women with a public
profile, there's a lot of that lower threshold harm coming
through. So those consistent comments.
So they might not be at the level where you think, "Oh, this is actually really
serious, and I need to take action," but they're quite consistent.
So that's what we heard is happening online quite a
bit. And so there are tools and things that young women
have used, and women in leadership have used alongside blocking.
But when people are moderating their pages,
there are options
that you can set up pages to work for you.
So in our Free to Lead toolkit, there's guidance around the spaces you
choose to be in, and you get to set the tone.
So there's things like creating community guidelines and making it really clear,
the people who are interacting with you, what you'll expect,
and what you'll put up with. And what we heard through some of the
engagement is that there is a lot of self-censorship after that takes place.
So, once somebody has put on their page, "I'm going to talk
about X, Y, Z. I won't be taking commentary
around my identity," or whatever that looks like, there's a lot of
self-moderation. And when those rules were in place, people noticed
a drop in some of that harmful commentary.
Yeah. Because what you find too, Mr.
Chair, is that
if you don't kick those comments out, those
negative ones out,
it then puts off people actually trying to make positive contributions.
Mm. Mm.
Positive contributions.
Yes.
And so,
it's almost self-fulfilling.
Yes.
So, they end up with the voice.
And so I don't tolerate it. But I'm
listening to you ladies talk about the toolkits and all this, but it
just seems so simple to me. Because we are in control.
Mm-hmm.
And we're trying to make-
But once it's there, it's there.
Yeah.
Yes, you can hide it, you can block them.
But when you're getting a barrage of hundreds and hundreds of comments
coming at you, yes, keep blocking, but the point is that they're making
those comments, and they're coming at you.
Well, you can't stop other people from commenting.
No, of course you can't. Of course you can't. You can't.
Oh, I'd like to make a last question, and then we might ad journal.
Oh.
No, I'm enjoying the conversation. I think it's a real one.
I think it's the way in which we should approach this, because I think so recently,
threats were made, and then the guy turned up out
on the forecourt, and I just wanted to go out and just drop him.
Now-
... that's just the real me.
Do it.
Yeah.
And I think what Catherine's saying, in our own ways, we're dealing with these
things, in
our own way, I guess.
But I guess, and I think about that, and then I'm noticing
the words I've circled, which is,
when you opened up, you talked about online harm, abuse, threat,
Free to Lead,
safety by design.
Mm.
See, already we're positioned in the back.
We're positioned behind the ball, and we're not-
And that's leadership, but it's this
not full out and lead, and there's no one else in the room.
Yeah.
I'm the only leader in the room.
Mm-hmm.
We don't get to that privilege yet.
I think it is a generational too. Sorry, my girlfriend says I'm good.
I think it is a generational thing.
I think there's this digital immigrant versus digital native.
Mm-hmm.
And I think that's also part of what you-
Mm-hmm
... witness when you're doing your work.
But what's my question? Actually, I don't
even know I've got one. I think there's a range of answers that already exist
inside of each of us, which I think I wouldn't mind.
You wouldn't want to say, "Look, just go out and drop them." Even though
there's something in that idea of taking it in our own
hands.
Mm-hmm.
And I know people get like, "Well, you can't just..." People get nervous
about women particularly wanting to be so proactive and
so
ordinary about being able to protect ourselves online, at
home, in our stores, at our clubs, wherever we happen to live.
So I
don't know whether any of where you're working goes to that
real end where the real harm exists.
Mm-hmm.
When you talked about misogyny, and we're doing some work around that, and I'm
like, "It's as plain as hell. We're screwed by it."
Mm-hmm.
And it is evident everywhere we work.
So
I didn't really get to my question, did I?
No, it's a good round.
I don't even know why I brought it.
It's okay.
I totally agree.
But you did raise-
A discussion.
Yeah.
It's absolutely about-
I think that it's a point well made in terms to of some of the language,
and fundamental for our work and how we want
to position it is to empower women-
Yep
... through information, through tools, through connections,
through communities, through storytelling.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
I teach, and I still teach self-defense to women and girls.
I've been teaching it for more than 35 years now.
Mm-hmm.
And across the country, actually.
And
the stories that I hear from those
women, and they're professional women, they're non-professional
women, and girls, and young girls, and kids in school,
and this is more than 30 or 40 years.
I
just don't see the progress that I wish-
Mm-hmm
... I would expect to see.
I would expect to see. I
don't get it.
Mm-hmm.
So yeah. I know what I'm going to be doing.
I'm just going to be teaching more self-defense,
both in your mind and in your body.
Absolutely.
Be able to protect yourself wherever you are.
Mm-hmm.
Good. Because I-
Well, that fits in well with-
Can I just wrap that up? I did a speech in the House about this once-
Mm
... a few years ago, and the only place that a
bully can survive is when they've got a victim.
So we've got to stop making women victims.
Um-
Which is what you're doing.
Public semester answer.
Yeah.
Sorry. I've got a thing next Tuesday, which is a movie on
strangulation.
Mm. Mm.
You are all absolutely welcome to come to it.
Thank you.
It is a documentary, and it's the first showing of it.
That's wonderful.
That's true of the whole committee.
I know it's tangential, but I think it's in the-
It's in the diary.
Yeah.
We've heard about it.
Thank you.
Thank you. Well, thank you very much for coming in and having a great discussion
this morning.
No, that's great.
Appreciate it.
You too.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.